A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Gene Wyckoff, Series 36 FA375
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Gene Wyckoff, Series 36
1961-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Boyd, Joseph H.
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
Ronan, William J. (William John)
Wyckoff, Gene
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Morrow, Hugh
Whitman, Ann
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Cannon, James M.
FA375
5 box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 36
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in two subseries:
Subseries 1 - "Executive Chamber" Program Files, 1961-1965 Subseries 2 - "Executive Chamber" Scripts and Related Materials, 1965-1965
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of Gene Wyckoff. They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series is a nearly complete representation of "Executive Chamber," a television program written and produced by Gene Wyckoff. Topics were worked out in conjunction with Governor Nelson Rockefeller and members of his staff. The programs, broadcast in late 1964 and 1965, were designed to make clear the Governor's position on issues of importance to New York State voters.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Public policy; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; State governments -- United States; Public relations; Arms control -- United States; Arms control; Civil defense -- United States; Civil defense; Civil service -- New York (State); Civil service; Federal government -- United States; Economics; Latin America; Legislation -- New York (State); International relations; International relations -- United States; Human rights; International economic relations; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Boyd, Joseph H.; New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service; Ronan, William J. (William John); Wyckoff, Gene; New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Morrow, Hugh; Whitman, Ann; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Cannon, James M.
- "Executive Chamber" Program Files, 1961-1965; 1; 3 box(es)
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged alphabetically by issue.
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries covers a variety of issues concerning New York State. It deals with topics that were covered by the "Executive Chamber" broadcasts as well as those considered for future shows.
  - Atomic Research and Development Authority Report, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Script for "Operation Sun Drum II"; Second Annual Report of the New York State Atomic Research and Development Authority; report, "Malta Test Station," New York State Atomic Research and Development Authority.
  - Criminal Justice System, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Report, "The New York State Identification and Intelligence System"; background information on New York State Corrections.
  - "Executive Chamber" #8 - Watkins Glen Scripts, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Drafts of "Executive Chamber" #8, 'A Walk in the Glen,' broadcast, May 1965.
  - "Executive Chamber" #8 - Watkins Glen - Selected Production Detail, Releases, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Background information, taping schedules, production follow-up on "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - Farm Labor, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Report, "A Helping Hand, Seasonal Farm Labor in New York State," November 1964; January 1964 issue of "Industrial Labor."
  - Financing, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Memorandum to Wyckoff enclosing NAR remarks on financial methods.
  - Human Rights, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence from Jerry Danzig to George Fowler, Commissioner of New York State Commission for Human Rights, on human rights topic for an "Executive Chamber" program.
  - Indians, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Report, "The Indian Today in New York State"; report, "Annual Report of New York State Interdepartmental Committee on Indian Affairs."
  - Mental Health, 1965; 1 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scripts, drafts, background materials, memorandum and reports, 'screen shots,' press releases on "Executive Chamber" #7, "The Troubled Mind," broadcast April 1965.
  - Mental Health, 1965; 2 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mental Health, 1965; 3 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mental Health, 1965; 4 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Music and Recording, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Music cue sheets for recordings used in production of "Executive Chamber" programs.
    Related Archival Materials note
    Nine record albums (78 rpm) were removed from this folder and are stored with the audio collection.
  - Narcotics, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Background information on Narcotics for possible used in a future "Executive Chamber" program.
  - New York State Transportation Association Maps and Timetables (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Airline timetables, New York State maps.
  - Park Development, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Memorandum to NAR from Laurance S. Rockefeller on park development in New York State.
  - Parks, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Report, "2 Year Progress Report on Land Acquisition for Parks and Recreation."
  - Scheduling, "Executive Chamber", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Background information, production notes on scheduling of the taping of "Executive Chamber" #8.
  - TV, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Correspondence and memoranda on production of "Executive Chamber" programs and their release to television outlets.
    Fourteen caption boards for the Executive Chamber series were removed from this folder and placed in box 5.
  - Water Pollution Film, 1964; 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Scripts, drafts, background materials, press releases on "Executive Chamber" #2, 'Little Drops of Water.'
  - Water Pollution Film, 1964; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Women, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Report, "New York Women and Their Changing World."
  - Photo Caption Boards - Executive Chamber (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Removed from Box 2, Folder 19.
  - Photo Caption Boards - Dr. William J. Ronan, Tri-State Transportation Committee (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Dr. Ronan (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Per Capita Aid (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Repeal of Full Crew Law (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photo Caption Boards - J. Burch McMorran, Supt. of Public Works (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Education (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Water Pollution (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Highway Safety (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Dr. James E. Allen, Jr., Commissioner of Education (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Dr. James E. Allen, Jr., Commissioner of Education (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Citizens Public Expenditure Survey, Inc., Albany (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Dr. Hollis S. Ingram, Commissioner of Health (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photo Caption Boards - Lawrence W. Pierce, Division of Youth (Box 5, Folder 14)
- "Executive Chamber" Scripts and Related Materials, 1964-1965; 2; 2 box(es)
  This subseries is arranged chronologically.
  This subseries contains scripts, production notes, and selected correspondence on the majority of the "Executive Chamber" programs that were broadcast. The production notes include such information as filming schedules, ideas on images and text to include in the various broadcasts, length of scenes in terms of both time and footage, sound and music suggestions, and production costs.
  - "Executive Chamber" #1, "How Much Education" - Scripts, November 1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Executive Chamber" #1, "How Much Education" - Production Notes, November 1964 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Executive Chamber" #1, "How Much Education" - Correspondence, November 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Executive Chamber" #2, "Little Drops of Water" - Scripts, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Executive Chamber" #2, "Little Drops of Water" - Production Notes, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Executive Chamber" #2, "Little Drops of Water" - Correspondence, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Executive Chamber" #3, "In the Name of the People" - Scripts, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Executive Chamber" #3, "In the Name of the People" - Production Notes, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Executive Chamber" #3, "In the Name of the People" - Correspondence, December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Executive Chamber" #4, "The View from the Governor's Chair" - Scripts, January 1965 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - "Executive Chamber" #4, "The View from the Governor's Chair" - Production Notes, January 1965 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "Executive Chamber" #4, "The View from the Governor's Chair" - Correspondence, January 1965 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "Executive Chamber" #4, "The View from the Governor's Chair" - Duplicate Bills for Reference, January 1965 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "Executive Chamber" #5, "The Troubled Mind" - Scripts, February 1965 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "Executive Chamber" #5, "The Troubled Mind" - Production Notes, February 1965 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Executive Chamber" #5, "The Troubled Mind" - Correspondence, February 1965 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Executive Chamber" #6, "The Transportation Tangle" - Scripts, March 1965 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Executive Chamber" #6, "The Transportation Tangle" - Production Notes, March 1965 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Executive Chamber" #6, "The Transportation Tangle" - Correspondence, March 1965 (Box 4, Folder 41)